<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The trayne souldier A sermon preached before the worthy societie of the captaynes and gentle men that exercise armes in the artillery garden. At Saint Andrew-vndershaft in London. Aprill 20. 1619. By I. Leech.</title>
            <author>Leech, Jeremy, d. 1644.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14422</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842537</idno>
  <idno type="VID">177049</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240864632</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 15364</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S106828</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99842537e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14422)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177049)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 769:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The trayne souldier A sermon preached before the worthy societie of the captaynes and gentle men that exercise armes in the artillery garden. At Saint Andrew-vndershaft in London. Aprill 20. 1619. By I. Leech.</title>
                  <author>Leech, Jeremy, d. 1644.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 69, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by J. B[eale] for Nathanaell Newbery, and are to be sold at the signe of the Starre vnder Saint Peters Church in Corne-hill, and in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The traine souldier.</note>
                  <note>Some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177049:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177049:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177049:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The trayne Souldier.</hi> A SERMON PREACHED <hi>Before the worthy Societie of</hi> the Captaynes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>men that exercise Armes in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery Garden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At Saint <hi>Andrew-vndershaft</hi> in London. <hi>Aprill.</hi> 20. 1619.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>I. Leech.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. KING. 20.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Let not him that girdeth on his harnesse boast as he that putteth it off.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted by <hi>J. B.</hi> for <hi>Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naell Newbery,</hi> and are to be sold at the signe of the Starre vnder Saint <hi>Peters Church</hi> in <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill,</hi> and in <hi>Popes-head</hi> Alley. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177049:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177049:3"/>
            <head>TO THE HEROICK AND TRVLY HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, <hi>GE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NERALL</hi> CE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CILL.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat in the publishing of this Sermon I haue thus aduenturingly presumed to front it with your name: others happily may question, your selfe wonder. Suffice it, that I can say of my Dedication, as our prudent Soueraign of his (if at lest I may dare with so vnworthy and rude a hand,
<note place="margin">In his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to his meditation vpon the Lords prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> to pluck a leafe from that royall Tree, &amp; sticke it in mine owne garland) that yet I haue <hi>obserued a decorum</hi> in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. The renowned fame of your military science and heroicall valour, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and confirmed vnto the world, by the mouthes of so many witnesses, suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently
<pb facs="tcp:177049:4"/>assures me that you haue <hi>an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in this argument,</hi> and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a meete person to whom I may make my dedication.</p>
            <p>For mine owne particular; I doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuously confesse, that to your noble selfe I am altogether an immeriting stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Yet seeing by the prouidence of God, you were an Auditor at this Sermon; and that it then pleased you to lend it your patient attention, afterward your fauourable approbation; loe now for a complement vnto both, I am further bold to craue for it your gentle patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage and protection Which if I may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, I shall not cease to pray for you, that you may long continue an honour, and ornament to your truely noble fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie; nor in any Christian seruice refuse, to be alwayes</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>At your honourable command,</hi> I. Leech.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177049:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL, And well accomplisht <hi>Gentleman, master</hi> Hugh HAMMERSLEY <hi>Sheriffe of</hi> LONDON, <hi>and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident</hi> of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery Society.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>TO THE WORTHY, and valorous, Captaine BING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAM, <hi>their vnderstanding Leader. AND</hi> TO ALL THE REST <hi>of that famous Societie, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</hi> Assistants, and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, professing and <hi>exercising Armes.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>WORTHY GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He vse of <hi>Musicke</hi> in the warres, is partly to direct the <hi>Souldier,</hi> partly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage him. Such I wisht
<pb facs="tcp:177049:5"/>this <hi>Sermon</hi> when I preacht it. Beside the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it for the fighting of spirituall battailes; That it might be as <hi>Musicke</hi> to encourage you in your other warlike preparations, and to breathe some little life into your generous spirits, though already brauely actuated with resolution and valour.</p>
            <p>It was yours from the beginning, and againe I make it yours. Yours in the bud, and yours in the fruit; in the seed yours, and yours in the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest. What you left scattered in the first reaping, you may now gleane vp againe, and not loose an eare in a surrow, if any way seruiceable for your vse.</p>
            <p>Of your fauourable acceptations I doubt not, comming from one that wishes a great deale of honour and happines, to euery member of your Societie, and to all your worthy designes. The poore <hi>Paynter</hi> could write vpon his <hi>Table,</hi> when he had embellisht it with the pictures of many rich Iems, <hi>Vellem &amp; haec.</hi> My <hi>velle</hi> is the same with his. I wish I could adde <hi>reall</hi> encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to these <hi>verball</hi> that I giue you. But it must suffice me to do as some <hi>Grecians</hi> were said to do, in their sacrifices to <hi>Hercules.</hi> They should
<pb facs="tcp:177049:5"/>haue offered to him, <hi>Oxen</hi> and <hi>Sheepe.</hi> Wanting at that time, they were faine to offer <hi>Melons</hi> and other fruites, cutting them into the shapes of <hi>Sheepe</hi> and <hi>Oxen,</hi> and fixing to their bodies little stickes of wood, artificially representing legs and feete; Such were the testimonies of their deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and zeale, and such the ieiune oblations, with which here I present you.</p>
            <p>In what euer they be defectiue, I shall endeuour to supply it, by my praying to God for you, as <hi>Moses</hi> prayde for the <hi>Israelites;</hi> Alwayes when they <hi>went forward</hi> in the Campe, that he would <hi>rise vp</hi> before them; alwayes when they <hi>rested</hi> that he would <hi>returne</hi> to them. So may he alwaies <hi>rise</hi> and alwayes <hi>returne</hi> vnto you both in your <hi>remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings</hi> &amp; in your <hi>restings.</hi> And the Lord make you all; (<hi>Captaines</hi> &amp; <hi>Souldiers, Leaders</hi> and <hi>Followers</hi>) such as the good <hi>Centurion</hi> was in the <hi>Gospell;</hi> such as the good <hi>Cornelius</hi> was in the <hi>Acts,</hi> deuout men, fearing God, &amp; full of faith &amp; good works. Then shall fiue of you be able to chase a hundred of your enemies, and a hundred of you to put ten thousand to flight.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your fellow-Souldier in the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes of our Lord Iesus, <hi>I. LEECH.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:177049:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177049:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The trayne Souldier.</hi> A SERMON PREACHED <hi>Before the worthy Societie of</hi> the Captaynes and <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that exercise Armes in the Artillery garden.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HEB. 12.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>You haue not yet resisted vnto Bloud.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hich text of Scripture if any thinke vnfit for this Assembly, as if there were some hint of <hi>exprobration</hi> in it, rather then of <hi>encouragement</hi> or <hi>dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> let my ingenuous defence bee
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177049:7"/>accepted. For matter of <hi>direction,</hi> I held not that so fit an argument for me to make choice of. Though there were fit matter for it in the Text, yet I were not fit for it. Who am I to giue <hi>direction</hi> in matters of <hi>Military discipline?</hi> I remember what <hi>Tullie</hi> writes of <hi>Phormio</hi> in his Booke <hi>de O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratore;</hi> When he made the Oration before <hi>Hannibal. Hannibal</hi> was one of the brauest captaines of the world. He told <hi>Scipio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch in vita Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal.</note> he held <hi>Alexander</hi> the best; <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> the second; himselfe the third: but he should haue held himselfe best, if he could haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Scipio. Scipio</hi> was well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with what he said, because hee saw that he neither contemn'd him, nor compard him, but left him peer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse in his censure. <hi>Phormio</hi> being to plead before <hi>Hannibal,</hi> be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke to giue instructions, about the ordering of Campes, the mustering of Souldiers, the marshalling of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and he did it very flourishing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177049:7"/>
               <hi>Hannibal</hi> was askt how he likt the Oration. He answerd, <hi>multos se de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liros audivisse,</hi> that he had heard ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dotards in his dayes, but none that doted like <hi>Phormio:</hi> A man that had neuer seene the warres in his life, yet would teach him to be a Warri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic. lib. de Orat.</hi> 2.</note> that had beene traind vp in feats of armes from his youth. To auoid that <hi>Indecorum</hi> therefore, I needed not a text of <hi>direction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For matter of <hi>exprobration;</hi> be it as farre from me as from the <hi>Apostle</hi> himselfe. But sure in this honey, there is none of that sting. Beloued, I come not to <hi>vpbraid,</hi> but to <hi>encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</hi> If I thought any <hi>viper of enuie</hi> would offer to leape vpon my hand. I should doe what I could to shake him off into the fire. That which seemes <hi>ad exprobrationem,</hi> is indeed <hi>ad excitationem.</hi> It is all to excite, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to vpbraid. So the <hi>Apostle</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth it, and so shall I be bold to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:177049:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Theophylact</hi> well obserues,
<note place="margin">Theophyl. in locum.</note> that he hath two sorts of arguments, for the encouraging of these Christians, to make them resolute Souldiers in Gods battles. The first drawne from that which <hi>themselues</hi> had sufferd. The next from that which <hi>others</hi> had sufferd. You haue the first in the 10. of this <hi>Epistle,</hi> verse 32. Hee speakes of a <hi>fight</hi> there, a <hi>fight of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions;</hi> a <hi>great fight of afflictions,</hi> which they <hi>themselues</hi> had endured: And he bids them call it to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, <hi>vt se ipsos imitarentur,</hi> that they might be still like themselues, and goe on as they had begun. The next is here in this Chapter; Here he proposeth vnto them that which <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> had endured, shewes that their sufferings were not yet like the suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of <hi>others,</hi> (for others <hi>had resisted vnto bloud;</hi> so had not they:) and this he presseth <hi>vt ne extollerentur,</hi> that they might not glory or <hi>presume</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themselues, but in stead of <hi>presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:177049:8"/>vpon any thing that was past, learne rather to <hi>prepare</hi> for the trials that were to come. In this then, as well as in that the <hi>Apostle</hi> coucheth a motiue of excitation and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement: In <hi>this</hi> when he tels them what they had <hi>not resisted,</hi> as well as in that, when hee telles them what they <hi>had endured.</hi> Because they had already <hi>endured</hi> somthing <hi>themselues,</hi> he exhorts them to bee constant as they had beene. Because they <hi>had not yet resisted</hi> so much as <hi>others,</hi> he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites them to <hi>prepare</hi> for what might be. <hi>You haue not yet, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They be two things that the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle</hi> principally aymes at.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>An intimation of the mercy that God had shewen:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>And an incitation to the dutie that they should learne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, It was a <hi>mercy of God</hi> to them, that being cald to the Christian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, and liuing (as they did) in a time of persecution, they had not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177049:9"/>yet drunke of the bitter cup, not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted of the <hi>bloudie tryall.</hi> Something they had sufferd for Christs sake,
<note place="margin">Gorran.</note> and a while they had stood it out, <hi>vs{que} ad rerum amissionem,</hi> as one sayes; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture to the losse of their sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance; yea but not <hi>vs{que} ad sanguinis effusionem,</hi> not to the shedding of their blood. For that, God had beene fauourable to them. Their <hi>bloud</hi> was not spilt, though their <hi>substance</hi> were spent. It had not cost them their <hi>liues,</hi> though they hadde lost their <hi>goods.</hi> Here was the <hi>Intimation of GODS mercie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now in this <hi>Intimation,</hi> there is an <hi>Incitation</hi> also. For from this which they had not done, the <hi>Apostle incites</hi> them to prepare for what they might doe. Tis true; They had <hi>not yet</hi> beene cald to any <hi>bloudie battle.</hi> But though they <hi>had not,</hi> were they sure they <hi>should not?</hi> Whether they should or no, he would haue them to prepare; for by <hi>preparing</hi> against a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177049:9"/>danger, we doe sometime <hi>preuent</hi> a danger.</p>
            <p>In teaching them this, he teacheth them three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To what manner of condition they were cald.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In this condition, what manner of conflict was required.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>In this conflict, what time of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance was expected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First. To what manner of <hi>conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> they were called?</p>
            <p>To a kinde of <hi>Martiall</hi> or <hi>Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry condition.</hi> They were called to be <hi>Warriours</hi> &amp; <hi>Souldiers.</hi> He that heares of <hi>bloud,</hi> and of <hi>resisting vnto bloud,</hi> he will easily conceiue that.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in this <hi>condition,</hi> what manner of <hi>conflict</hi> must they vse? It must be <hi>a conflict of resistance;</hi> impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>assaults</hi> would be made vpon them, and therefore that when the enemie offerd to <hi>assault,</hi> they should be in a readinesse to <hi>resist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, for the <hi>vs{que}</hi> How long is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177049:10"/>it expected, that they must continue in the <hi>conflict? Vs{que} ad finem,</hi> sayes our Sauiour:
<note place="margin">Matth. 24.13.</note> It must be to <hi>the end. Vs{que} ad sanguinem</hi> sayes the <hi>Apostle:</hi> It must be to <hi>bloud,</hi> if God will haue it to be <hi>a bloudie end.</hi> They be not a few <hi>resistances</hi> that can crowne vs, nor a few <hi>losses</hi> that must excuse vs. The <hi>resistance</hi> must be <hi>finall;</hi> the <hi>losse totall.</hi> We must be willing to loose all; all for Christs sake, our friendes and freedomes, lands and liuings, lymbes and liues. No <hi>nil vltra</hi> till then.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You haue not yet resisted vnto bloud. You haue not,</hi> sayes the Apostle. But though you haue not, <hi>others</hi> haue. Looke what hath happened vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the same may happen vnto you. You haue not <hi>yet,</hi> sayes the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle. But though you haue not <hi>yet,</hi> you may <hi>hereafter. Hodie mihi, cras ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi;</hi> It is my turne to day, it may be yours to morrow. You haue not <hi>yet resisted</hi> sayes the Apostle. <hi>Persisted</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:177049:10"/>you haue a while, you haue continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and gone on in your Christian <hi>profession.</hi> But <hi>resisting</hi> you haue not yet beene put to. You haue not yet beene encounterd with any strong <hi>opposition.</hi> Or you haue not yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted <hi>vnto bloud</hi> sayes the <hi>Apostle.</hi> Some <hi>resistances</hi> you haue made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, sufferd some labours, some losses. Yea but still your life hath bin giuen you for a pray; you neuer came into a <hi>bloudie Skirmish.</hi> Ther's the valour of a Souldier to be tryed. <hi>Skin for skin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 2.4.</note>
               <hi>and all that a man hath he will part withall, for the sauing of his life.</hi> Perhaps it is your life that God will haue you to lay downe; it is a <hi>bloudie sacrifice</hi> that hee lookes for. As you haue beene baptisde with <hi>water,</hi> he will haue you baptisde with <hi>bloud.</hi> This you must expect; for this you must prepare.</p>
            <p>I haue shewen you the frame of the <hi>Apostles</hi> argument, taken all the peices of it asunder as you see. I must
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177049:11"/>now set it together againe, and into euery ioynt of that fasten a peice of mine owne. Mine shall answere his as <hi>face answers face.</hi> The Apostle in his argument borrowes from <hi>Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and applyes it to <hi>Christians.</hi> I hope I may take what he borrowes, and when it hath done seruice vnto them, bring it home vnto you. The <hi>resistance</hi> and <hi>bloud</hi> that he speaks of, he meanes it not in the <hi>literall</hi> sence, but in the <hi>spirituall.</hi> I will first han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle it in the sence that he meanes it, and when I haue done with it in his, I will fit it to ours. It shall haue his vse in the <hi>letter</hi> as well as in the <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory.</hi> So with one labour I shall dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch two workes, with one hand spyn two threds; I shall draw the sword both for <hi>God,</hi> and for <hi>Gideon.</hi> Something I shall commend vnto you that may accommodate you for the <hi>spirituall</hi> warfare; teach you to be good Souldiers, vnder that <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne,</hi> spoken of in the beginning of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177049:11"/>the Chapter, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;
<note place="margin">Verse 2.</note> Christ Iesus, the <hi>Captayne of our faith:</hi> And something I shall say for the exercise of this <hi>bodily,</hi> this <hi>worldly</hi> warfare, and the necessary preparations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto pertaining; that you may bee good Souldiers likewise for your <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> if GOD will haue a tryall of your seruice; though therein I confesse rather as an <hi>Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rager,</hi> then as a <hi>Teacher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The two principall points that I began with, I hope you haue not yet forgot. Those are as the <hi>two staues</hi> put into their <hi>two rings,</hi> vpon which the <hi>Arke of my discourse</hi> must be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed. First, An <hi>Intimation of GODS mercy:</hi> For that the Apostle notes when he sayes, they had <hi>not yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted vnto bloud.</hi> It was <hi>Gods mercie</hi> they had not. Then, <hi>an Incitation of them vnto their dutie.</hi> For though they had not <hi>yet,</hi> they might <hi>after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> And what better wisedome then to prouide against after-incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences?</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:177049:12"/>
            <p>Of <hi>Gods mercy first. You haue not yet resisted.</hi> Sure this was a great <hi>mercy</hi> of God to these Christians, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how it had pleased him to deale with others. Looke but the former <hi>Chapter,</hi> and there you shall reade of others that had <hi>resisted.</hi> It is a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Chapter, where the <hi>Apostle</hi> brings in <hi>Faith</hi> riding in a Chariot of triumph with a Crowne vpon her head, and a troupe of Souldiers attending her in their rankes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. They come out in their two bands. The first all in <hi>white,</hi> like him vpon the <hi>White Horse; Apoc.</hi> 6. There was a <hi>Bow and a Crowne giuen him, and he went out to conquer.</hi> The next all <hi>in red,</hi> like him vpon the <hi>red horse</hi> in the fourth <hi>verse</hi> of the same <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> He had power giuen him to <hi>take peace from the Earth, and to kill with the Sword.</hi> Both of them <hi>conquered</hi> by their <hi>Faith:</hi> That is sure; both they of the <hi>White band,</hi> and they of the <hi>Red.</hi> But the one <hi>Ardua operando,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:177049:12"/>the other <hi>Difficilia sustinendo;</hi> the one by acting heroically, the other by suffering couragiously. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore marke how the <hi>Apostle</hi> brings them in, at the 36 <hi>verse</hi> of that <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Hee brings them with their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours torne, their plumes rent, their swords hackt, their armes batterd, their flesh gasht, their limbes burst, their bodies wounded and scard. They haue brands and markes vpon them, of <hi>racking, torturing, hewing, stoning, scourging, imprisoning:</hi> These were warriours indeede, one might see these were come from a battell, where there had beene <hi>tumbling of garments in bloud.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esa. 9.5.</note> These had stoutly <hi>resisted vnto bloud.</hi> Looke vpon these saith the <hi>Apostle; You haue not thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, looke but the beginning of this <hi>Chapter.</hi> There is <hi>Vnus instar om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium,</hi> one that may stand for all. No <hi>Souldier</hi> of the band, but the <hi>Captaine</hi> of the band; the <hi>Captaine</hi> &amp; <hi>Crowner
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177049:13"/>of our Faith;</hi> looke how hee resisted. When wee looke at him, wee may aske as the <hi>Prophet</hi> did, and wonder as we aske;
<note place="margin">Esa. 63.1.</note>
               <hi>VVho is this? This that comes vp from Edom, with red gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from Bozrah? His garments are all red, and his apparell like one that had troden the wine presse: The bloud is sprinckled vpon his apparell, and all his garments are stained.</hi> If euer there were <hi>bloudy resistance,</hi> it was when <hi>Christ</hi> fought the battell. He <hi>resisted</hi> with a witnesse, <hi>resisted vnto bloud;</hi> and that more then once or twice.</p>
            <p>I name not the blood of his <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcision.</hi> That was in <hi>Praesepio,</hi> when he lay but in the <hi>Cradle,</hi> in the <hi>Cratch,</hi> you will thinke it was but weake <hi>resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance</hi> he made then: But that at his <hi>death and passion,</hi> when he was put to strong and violent <hi>resistances;</hi> first, in <hi>Horte,</hi> then in <hi>Pratorie,</hi> then in <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulo.</hi> In <hi>horto,</hi> in the <hi>Garden;</hi> there he resisted; there his <hi>agony</hi> drew <hi>bloud</hi> from him, it cast him into a sweate;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177049:13"/>be swet till he dropt, swet till he <hi>bled.</hi> They were <hi>Grumi sanguinis,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, saith the Text, thicke drops of bloud, that trilled from his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to the ground. Then in <hi>Praetorio,</hi> in the <hi>Iudgement Hall;</hi> there hee resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted: There the <hi>thornes</hi> and the <hi>whips</hi> drew blood from him. They plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a wreath of <hi>thornes</hi> vpon his head, and his bodie they all scourged with <hi>whips.</hi> How could the blood but gush out being so mangled, so rent with <hi>whips and thornes?</hi> Finally, <hi>In Patibulo;</hi> vpon the <hi>Crosse,</hi> there he <hi>resisted:</hi> There the <hi>nayles</hi> &amp; the <hi>speare</hi> drew <hi>bloud</hi> from him; the <hi>nayles</hi> from his hands and feete, the <hi>speare</hi> from his side. It was <hi>precious bloud</hi> he shed then. The losse of that, cost him the losse of his life. So here was another that <hi>resisted vnto bloud,</hi> and this infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely excelling those that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Those before, they were but <hi>Serui,</hi> though <hi>Sancti;</hi> though <hi>Saints,</hi> yet but <hi>Seruants.</hi> This the <hi>Prince of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177049:14"/>our saluation,</hi> the <hi>Sonne of the Father,</hi> the <hi>Lord of glory,</hi> the <hi>heire of all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In opposition vnto both these, the <hi>Apostle</hi> tels the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> that <hi>they had not thus resisted.</hi> Not <hi>they,</hi> though <hi>others;</hi> not <hi>they,</hi> though <hi>Christ</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe. So intimating that God had dealt more fauourably with <hi>them</hi> then with <hi>others;</hi> yea, more fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably with <hi>them,</hi> then with his owne <hi>Sonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.32.</note>
               <hi>whom he spared not, but gaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the death.</hi> That immaculate and blessed Sonne of his, that was <hi>in all things without sinne;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note> yet not <hi>Sine fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gello,</hi> though <hi>Sine peccato:</hi> though without sinne, not without suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; but he suffered, and <hi>resisted. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistendo sustinuit, sustinendo restitit:</hi> In <hi>resisting,</hi> hee suffered; in suffering, he <hi>resisted:</hi> Hee <hi>resisted vnto bloud.</hi> And why was all this? this that they suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered? this that hee suffered? why but to teach these <hi>Hebrewes</hi> a lesson of <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>thankefulnesse? Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:177049:14"/>to endure that which God did inflict: <hi>Thankefulnesse,</hi> for not being put to endure that which God might inflict.</p>
            <p>Was this for the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> onely, and is it not for vs also? Yes, euen for vs also. The <hi>Doue</hi> hath long sitten vpon our <hi>Arke</hi> with an <hi>Oliue branch</hi> in her mouth. The <hi>Gospell</hi> hath long flourisht among vs, with a great deale of happinesse and freedome. Many, many yeers together, we haue stood and setled vpon our lees, and not beene <hi>poured out from vessell to vessell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 48.11.</note> We haue seene <hi>Truth</hi> &amp; <hi>Peace</hi> met together in our Church, liued in the <hi>Halcyon-dayes</hi> of the World, when no tempest hath troubled the face of the water. <hi>God hath not dealt thus with euery Nation;</hi> not with our <hi>Fathers</hi> before vs, not with our <hi>neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours</hi> about vs. Can those <hi>Marian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times</hi> bee yet forgotten, when the poore persecuted <hi>Church,</hi> like the <hi>Woman; Reuel.</hi> 12.14. was faine to get
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177049:15"/>her <hi>the wings of an Eagle, and to flie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wildernesse,</hi> lest the <hi>Dragon should deuour the children of which shee trauailed?</hi> When in this very <hi>Citie</hi> which is now a <hi>Sanctuary for religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> there were stakes of Martyrdome continually flaming, and <hi>the bloud of the Saints shed in the streets of it!</hi> Such were the dayes of our <hi>Fathers;</hi> But we haue <hi>not so resisted.</hi> Can we at this instant bee insensible of what our neighbouring Nations do beare and groane vnder; Those in <hi>France,</hi> those in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and in other Countries about vs?
<note place="margin">Pro. 23 34.</note> They be like <hi>men that fleepe in the top of a Mast;</hi> enuironed with feares, and encompast with dangers. Though they haue the <hi>foode of the Gospell,</hi> yet it is like the <hi>Iewish Passouer</hi> vnto them; They are faint to eate it with the <hi>bread of trembling;</hi> and with the <hi>sweete flesh</hi> that is giuen them, a great many <hi>bitter hearbes</hi> there bee mingled. Few yeares, few moneths, but some bloudy sacrifices are offerd
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177049:15"/>to appease the fury of their Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Such be the tryals of <hi>our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren:</hi> But we haue not so <hi>resisted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heare then <hi>oh Israel,</hi> what it is that God requires at thy hand for this his lenitie and long suffering; What <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> he requires; What <hi>thankfulnes</hi> he requires. Did I say <hi>what patience?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. in Moral.</note> Alas, <hi>Nunquam est Patientiae virtus in prosperis.</hi> There is no vse of <hi>patience,</hi> while the times are prosperous and peaceable: Till the Steele strike vpon the flint, who can tell what sparkes of fire will flie out; If once we be put to the triall, then let <hi>patience</hi> haue her worke. Then confesse, it is but little thou endurest, considering how much thou deseru'st. <hi>Si bene conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur culpa, patienter toleratur poena.</hi> If we consider well of our sinne, wee wil easily submit to the punishment: And the punishment we suffer then, it shall not be <hi>Poena</hi> but <hi>Poenitenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> rather penitence for sinne, then pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment of sinne. Acknowledge
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177049:16"/>then thy suffering is but little (though much, yet but little) consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what others before thee haue suffered, especially considering what the <hi>Lord Iesus</hi> himselfe hath endurd. <hi>Si passto Redemptoris in memoriam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducitur, nihil tam durum est quod non aequo animo toleratur.</hi> The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Christs passion will helpe to mitigate any paine. And in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie of all paine, let this euer bee thy comfort first, That whatsoeuer it be thou sufferst, if thou be <hi>Christs, Christ</hi> suffers with thee. <hi>Patitur in te qui passus est pro te.</hi> He suffers with thee who suffered for thee. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Whatsoeuer it be thou sufferest, if it be <hi>for him,</hi> thou shalt haue thy reward <hi>from him.</hi> As he leads thee the way, so he will giue thee the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.
<note place="margin">Bern. in Canti.</note>
               <hi>Vtrum{que} mihi es Domine Iesu, &amp; speculum patiendi, &amp; praemium patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti;</hi> as most sweetly S. <hi>Bernard.</hi> Thou art both to me oh Lord Iesus, both an example of suffering, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in suffering.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:177049:16"/>
            <p>In the meane time, <hi>Thankefulnesse, Thankefulnesse;</hi> That is the present grace that we haue need of. Though all blessings challenge <hi>Thankefulnes</hi> at our handes, yet none more then this. This I say, that as we haue <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelium pacis,</hi> the Gospell of peace among vs, so <hi>Pacem Evangelij</hi> the peace of the Gospell; That none needs to <hi>resist,</hi> because none offers to <hi>assault. O fortunatos bona si sua no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint.</hi> Happie, happie we were, if we knew our owne happines. Beloued. It is not with vs as with <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 120.5.</note> We are not constrained to dwell in <hi>Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hech</hi> and <hi>Kedar.</hi> We need not wish our selues <hi>dore-keepers in Gods house:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 84.3.10.</note> nor enuie the <hi>Sparrows</hi> and the <hi>Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows</hi> for their roosting and building within the walles of the <hi>Tabernacle.</hi> We are daily witnesses how <hi>glorious the goings of God are in his Sanctuarie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 68.24.</note> Daily we doe <hi>behold the beautie of his house, and visit his Temple.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 27.4.</note>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 128.5.</note> We haue <hi>seene Ierusalem in prosperitie all our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177049:17"/>life long, and peace vpon Israell.</hi> If euer therefore we forget this mercie of God toward vs, <hi>let our right hand for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get her cunning.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 137.5.</note> If we remember not to be thankfull to him for this, <hi>let our tongue cleaue to the roofe of our mouth, yea if we prefer not this to our chiefest ioy.</hi> And Lord, as aboue all, we desire to be thankfull for this; so aboue all, make vs still happie in this. Let the <hi>Arke of thy presence</hi> alwayes goe before vs;
<note place="margin">Cant. 2.12.</note> and let this <hi>voyce of the Turtle be euer heard in our land.</hi> If our sinnes must needes haue a scourge, yet Lord let it not bee this scourge, not the <hi>persecuting of thy Gospell.</hi> Let it be plague, or famine, or fire, or any thing rather then this. Till the starres fall from Heauen, let this <hi>Manna</hi> of heauen neuer cease to fall. Oh keepe vs in these pastures, lead vs to these waters, guide vs with this staffe, gouerne vs with this rod, let this cloud goe before vs, let this light shine about vs, and about our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177049:17"/>that shall rise vp after vs, from generation to generation, euen vnto the end of the world; Say <hi>Amen</hi> to it thou <hi>faithfull witnesse of heauen;</hi> and all that haue hearts to wish it, let them say, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue done with the first poynt; the <hi>Intimation of Gods mercy:</hi> That which the <hi>Apostle</hi> here would haue the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> to take note of, in that it pleased him when he had prest out others into his battles, yet to spare &amp; exempt them.
<note place="margin">Gen. 33.2.</note> He dealt by them as <hi>Iacob</hi> dealt by <hi>Rachel</hi> &amp; <hi>Ioseph,</hi> when he went out to meet <hi>Esau.</hi> He put them <hi>hindmost in the company.</hi> By o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as <hi>Dauid</hi> by <hi>Vriah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.15.</note> when he laid siege against <hi>Rabbah,</hi> he put him <hi>into the forefront of the Battell.</hi> That they were thus fauourably dealt withall, they rather then others (o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>resisting vnto bloud,</hi> when they resisted not) it was a speciall <hi>mercy of God</hi> toward them, and the Apostle would haue them to consider it.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177049:18"/>Consider it sayes the <hi>Apostle. You haue not yet resisted vnto bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now with the <hi>intimation of Gods mercy,</hi> here is also an <hi>incitation of them vnto their dutie.</hi> God had not yet cald them into any <hi>battell of bloud.</hi> True, But though he had not, were they sure he would not? Because they now dwelt in safetie, could they therefore promise vnto themselues any future securitie? If they could not, as indeed they could not (for who can <hi>boast of to morrow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27.1.</note>
               <hi>when he knows not what a day may bring forth?</hi>) notwithstanding their present imu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie; it would be safe for them to prepare against subsequent dangers. So they should shewe themselues <hi>prouident</hi> indeed. For <hi>Prouidence,</hi> is but <hi>Porro videns,</hi> as the Notation giues it.</p>
            <p>To prepare for them the better, they must take into consideration these three things. 1. To what <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of condition</hi> they are called. 2. In
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177049:18"/>this <hi>condition</hi> what manner of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict</hi> is required. 3. In this <hi>conflict</hi> what time of <hi>continuance</hi> is expected. For their <hi>condition,</hi> it is the <hi>condition of Warriours.</hi> For their <hi>conflict,</hi> it must be a <hi>conflict of resistance.</hi> For their <hi>continuance,</hi> they must <hi>continue it vnto bloud.</hi> So then <hi>conditio mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandi;</hi> this is the first. <hi>Conflictus resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendi;</hi> this is the second. <hi>Virtus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuandi;</hi> this is the third.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conditio militandi.</hi> To begin with that. The <hi>condition</hi> they were called to. They were called to be <hi>Souldiers</hi> and <hi>Warriours.</hi> This is a point (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) necessarily implyed, though not literally exprest. When the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle</hi> speakes of <hi>striuing,</hi> of <hi>resisting,</hi> of <hi>resisting vnto bloud,</hi> to whom can this appertaine, but to those of the Military profession, <hi>Warriours</hi> and <hi>Souldiers.</hi> The resultance therefore must be this, <hi>That when we are called to be Christians, we are called to bee Souldiers.</hi> And this is first of all for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177049:19"/>the <hi>Souldiers</hi> honour. Whosoeuer is a profest <hi>Christian,</hi> he is a profest <hi>Souldier;</hi> or if no <hi>Souldier,</hi> no <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> You know what <hi>S. Paul</hi> sayes of himselfe; He sayes that he had beene in the <hi>fight:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.7.</note> and that he had <hi>fought a good fight.</hi> He had beene a <hi>Souldier</hi> therefore; and so he encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages <hi>Timothy</hi> to be likewise; <hi>Learne to suffer hardnesse,</hi> sayes he, <hi>like a good Souldier of Iesus Christ.</hi> 2. Tim. 2.3. Nay, and as euery <hi>Christian</hi> is a <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier;</hi> so the whole <hi>Church of Christ,</hi> is as an <hi>Armie of Souldiers.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> mililant; that is the proper attribute of it. And we find it compard to an Armie. Cant. 6.3. <hi>Thou art beautifull my loue as Tirzah, comely as Ierusalem, terrible as an armie with banners.</hi> Nay, not the <hi>Church</hi> onely, but the <hi>Angels</hi> themselues, they are called <hi>Souldiers.</hi> A multitude of <hi>heauenly Souldiers</hi> praising God: <hi>Luc.</hi> 2.13. Nay, not the <hi>Angels</hi> onely, but <hi>Christ</hi> himselfe; he is the <hi>Captaine-Souldier.</hi> The <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177049:19"/>of the Lords hoast:</hi> Iosh. 5.15. Nay not <hi>Chrst</hi> onely, but the <hi>Lord God</hi> himselfe; Though <hi>Deus pacis,</hi> the God of peace; <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20. yet <hi>vir belli;</hi> a man of warre. <hi>Iehovah is a man of warre, Iehovah is his name.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odus 15.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Christians are Souldiers.</hi> Looke therefore what belongs to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contrement of a <hi>Souldier;</hi> that to the furniture of a <hi>Christian.</hi> Secondly, there are foure things that hee must be prouided of. He must haue <hi>armes.</hi> He must haue <hi>strength.</hi> He must haue <hi>courage.</hi> He must haue <hi>skill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, <hi>Armes</hi> are necessary. There is no going out against an enemie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vn-weapond. If you aske what <hi>Armes;</hi> let Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tell you; <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.11. I referre you no whither but thither. There is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>whole armour</hi> of God; armour both <hi>defensiue</hi> and <hi>offensiue,</hi> both to guard our selues, and to foyle our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:177049:20"/>
            <p>Secondly, with <hi>armes,</hi> hee must haue <hi>strength</hi> too. Else his armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him wil be but like <hi>Sauls</hi> about <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.39.</note> He will not be able to weild them.
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note> Tis not bodily <hi>strength</hi> I speake of. That <hi>auayles nothing to this combate;</hi> No, not though our <hi>strength were as the strength of stones, and our flesh as brasse;</hi> as it is <hi>Iob</hi> 6.12. It is <hi>spirituall strength</hi> that we must get vs; I meane the <hi>strength of Gods spirit;</hi> therefore cald the <hi>spirit of strength.</hi> Esa. 11.2. Without this, we are like <hi>Sampson</hi> without his lockes, and our <hi>strength</hi> is but as the <hi>strength</hi> of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men. What was it that <hi>Sampson</hi> could not doe, as long as his <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites fleece</hi> was vn-shorne? The spirit of God was vpon him then; sayes the Scripture.
<note place="margin">Iudg. 14.6.</note> Then he could haue <hi>rent a Lyon as one would haue rent a Kyd;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 16.3.</note> he could carry away the <hi>gates of Azzah</hi> vpon his backe, with the <hi>postes</hi> and the <hi>barres</hi> of it, be could slay a <hi>thousand Philistimes with the
<note place="margin">Chap. 15.15</note>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:177049:20"/>I aw bone of an Asse.</hi> But when once the <hi>spirit of the Lord</hi> was departed from him, what was <hi>Sampson</hi> more then another man? Thus we. As long as we goe on in the <hi>strength of Gods spirit,</hi> it is not <hi>Sathan,</hi> the roaring <hi>Lyon</hi> that can hurt vs; They be not the <hi>gates of Azzah,</hi> the <hi>gates of Hell,</hi> that can preuaile against vs. They be not a <hi>thousand Philistimes, a thousand tentations</hi> that can either <hi>discomfit,</hi> or <hi>discomfort</hi> vs. But if that assist vs not, what are we more then others? We are but like <hi>Reedes shaken with the winde.</hi> If we can be therefore as S. <hi>Paul</hi> sayes, <hi>strong in the Lord, and in the power of his might.</hi> Ephe. 6.10. We may then boast as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> does, that we shall be able to doe all thinges by the vertue of that power. <hi>I can doe all things through him that strengthens me.</hi> Phil. 4.13.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as he must haue <hi>strength</hi> so he must haue <hi>courage.</hi> Without <hi>courage, strength</hi> is nothing. What is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177049:21"/>a <hi>Lions strength,</hi> with a <hi>Hares spirit? Resolution</hi> and <hi>Courage</hi> is the best weapon that a man can carry into the field with him.
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 21.9.</note> We may say of it as <hi>Dauid</hi> of <hi>Goliahs</hi> sword: <hi>There is none to that.</hi> Now the <hi>courage</hi> of a <hi>Christian,</hi> is from the testimonie of a <hi>good conscience.</hi> That is <hi>murus ahene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> It is a wall of brasse about him: Nay, it is a <hi>wall of fire,</hi> to keepe off all that shall come neere him.
<note place="margin">Pro. 28.1.</note>
               <hi>Salomon</hi> rels vs, it will make one <hi>bold as a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; bold</hi> against the accusations of men, nay <hi>bold</hi> against the accusations of <hi>Sathan,</hi> nay <hi>bold</hi> in the presence of <hi>God</hi> himselfe. <hi>If our conscience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs not, we haue boldnesse toward God:</hi> 1. Ioh. 3.21. To the braue-spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited <hi>Souldier,</hi> there is nothing more hatefull then the name of a <hi>Coward</hi> If you would not be <hi>Cowards</hi> when you come into the field, but looke your enemie <hi>couragiously</hi> in the face, be sure you keepe a <hi>good conscience</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you. Carry not <hi>letters in your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somes</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:177049:21"/>that will betray you into the hands of those that hate you.
<note place="margin">Nemo tam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dax quem ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la conscientia non facit timi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dissimum.</note> Onely he can haue a <hi>good courage</hi> that hath a <hi>good conscience:</hi> Else, as it was sayd to <hi>Phocas</hi> about his high building; <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum intus;</hi> The sinne within will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow all.</p>
            <p>Lastly, with all these, he must haue <hi>wisedome</hi> and <hi>skill.</hi> This is also as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for <hi>Campes</hi> as for <hi>Courts,</hi> for <hi>Souldiers</hi> as for <hi>Senators. Armes</hi> are to little purpose, <hi>Strength</hi> to little purpose; <hi>Courage</hi> to little purpose, if for the <hi>skilful</hi> managing of all these there want <hi>discretion</hi> and <hi>wisedome. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulius Caesar</hi> knew it well: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he went out against <hi>Afra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> he said, he went in <hi>exercitum si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Duce;</hi> to an armie without a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. There was a <hi>body of strength,</hi> but there wanted a <hi>head of skill:</hi> But when against <hi>Pompey,</hi> then <hi>ad ducem sine exercitu,</hi> to a Captaine without an Armie: There was a <hi>head of skill,</hi> but there wanted a <hi>bodie of strength.</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:177049:22"/>Will you haue it from the mouth of an <hi>Oracle?</hi> haue it from <hi>Salomon</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe. Eccles. 9.13. <hi>I haue seene a little Cittie, and a great King hath besieged it. There was a poore, wise man found that deliuered the Cittie by his wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Then I sayd wisedome is better then strength.</hi> The <hi>wisedome</hi> that a <hi>spirituall Warriour</hi> must haue, he must haue it from the holy <hi>word of God.</hi> From the assistance of <hi>Gods spirit,</hi> thence he must haue <hi>strength.</hi> From the testimony of a <hi>good conscience,</hi> thence he must haue <hi>courage.</hi> From the direction of <hi>Gods word,</hi> thence he must haue <hi>wisedome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh therefore acquaint your selues with the holy <hi>word of God,</hi> and get to be familiar in the rules of it. As it will make you wiser then your <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 119.98.</note> wiser then your <hi>Teachers,</hi> so <hi>wiser then your enemies.</hi> The <hi>Enemie</hi> himselfe you see, knowing of what power the word is, he does often make vse of it. But as it is sayd of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177049:22"/>
               <hi>Epaminondas</hi> that he drew the Darts out of his owne bodie,
<note place="margin">Plut. in vita Epaminon. Sic &amp; Brasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, hastâ è suo extracta corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re eum ipsum percutit ac ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit, à quo in ipsum fucrat missa. Apud Plut. De his qui sero a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nime puniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> which the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> had throwne at him, and threw them backe againe to the wounding of the <hi>Lacedemonians;</hi> so the Darts which the <hi>Enemy</hi> throwes at vs, when he sights against vs with the <hi>word,</hi> by the <hi>skilfull</hi> vse of it we may learne to retort them vpon him againe, and so beate him out of the field with his owne weapon. There is no <hi>Enemy</hi> can come against vs but this will put him to the foyle. It will teach <hi>our hands to warre, and our fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to fight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You see the <hi>condition</hi> of a <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an:</hi> He is a <hi>Souldier.</hi> Next, see the <hi>conflict</hi> that he maks. From the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is a <hi>conflict of resistance.</hi> And this is the second point that I considered of: <hi>Conflictus resistendi; Resistance</hi> presupposes an <hi>assault:</hi> For vnlesse there bee <hi>assaults</hi> offered vs, what need wee to resist? I demand therefore; Who be they that <hi>assault</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:177049:23"/>vs? Beloued, we are subiect to a two-fold <hi>assault: An assault of Sinners, An assault of Sinne.</hi> The Apostle men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions both: That of <hi>Sinne,</hi> in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of this verse; <hi>We striue against Sinne:</hi> That of <hi>Sinners,</hi> a little before in the precedent verse; Where hee sayes of Christ, that he endured the <hi>contradictions of Sinners.</hi> Indeed <hi>Christ</hi> had <hi>Sinners to resist,</hi> but not <hi>Sinne. Sinne</hi> could make no <hi>assault</hi> vpon <hi>Christ:</hi> for as in life, so in nature he was pure and vndefiled. We haue to <hi>resist</hi> both; both <hi>Sinners,</hi> and <hi>Sin.</hi> The way to <hi>resist Sinners,</hi> is by <hi>not resisting.</hi> The way to <hi>resist Sinne,</hi> is by <hi>not consenting.</hi> If malicious and wicked <hi>Sinners</hi> do at any time <hi>assault</hi> or set vpon vs, either with the <hi>sword of Ismaell,</hi> a reviling tongue; or with the <hi>sword of Esau,</hi> a persecuting hand; what haue we to doe? Not to <hi>desist</hi> from our innocence, nor to <hi>resist</hi> them with violence. When we doe <hi>not resist,</hi> then we doe <hi>resist.</hi> Submit
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177049:23"/>with <hi>patience</hi> to endure their <hi>persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> but fall not away with <hi>diffidence</hi> from the truth of thy <hi>profession.</hi> When the tentations of <hi>Sin</hi> do <hi>assault</hi> vs, our <hi>resisting</hi> then is our <hi>not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting.</hi> So long as we <hi>consent not</hi> to the <hi>suggestions</hi> of <hi>Sinne,</hi> so long we make <hi>resistance</hi> against them. <hi>Bare suggestions are no Sinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, it is a difficult thing to be a <hi>good Souldier;</hi> by consequent to be a <hi>good Christian.</hi> So you may gather by this. He must be <hi>in vtrum{que} para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> euery way prouided as you see, both <hi>ad faciendum,</hi> and <hi>ad patiendum,</hi> both to doe, and to suffer. In <hi>resisting</hi> against <hi>Sin,</hi> there he must be an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent;</hi> in <hi>resisting</hi> against <hi>Sinners,</hi> there he must be a <hi>Patient.</hi> Little doe Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures &amp; worldlings know, our wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and delicate Professors, such as <hi>liue at ease in Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 6.1.</note> little do they know what belongs either to the one or to the other. Yet we for our parts must know it, and not onely know it, but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177049:24"/>professe it, and not onely professe it, but practise it.
<note place="margin">Plut. in vita Hannibal.</note>
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> writes of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> that being but a <hi>Childe,</hi> his father at a sacrifice made him sweare, that when he came to mans state, he would be a mortall enemie to the <hi>Romanes.</hi> Let's remember we haue all taken the like oath; we in the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,</hi> as he at the <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> Euen while we were <hi>Children</hi> you know, and had the <hi>Sacrament of Baptisme</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministerd vpon vs, we did then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise and sweare vnto God, that we would be mortall enemies to <hi>Sinne</hi> and <hi>Sathan,</hi> and manfully fight his battels against all that should oppose vs.</p>
            <p>I! but <hi>vsquequo Domine, vsquequo?</hi> How long <hi>Lord,</hi> how long must this <hi>conflict</hi> continue, must this <hi>resistance</hi> endure? I am now gotten to the last poynt of all, the <hi>virtus continuandi.</hi> You see I doe but <hi>summa sequi fasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia rerum;</hi> I doe but crop a few prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall heads; cull here a berry, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177049:24"/>there a berry, but the greatest part of the fruit I leaue vngathered, because I would not haue the vintage too long. For the time of <hi>continuance</hi> therefore, it must be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to the end,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, sayes the <hi>Apostle vnto bloud.</hi> Peraduenture God will haue vs die in the maintenance of his quarrell, he wil haue vs witnesse it with our liues, seale it with our <hi>blouds.</hi> Be it so. It shall be with vs as with <hi>Epaminondas;</hi> wee shall conquer though we die. Neuer let the blast of such a threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning discourage vs; neuer let it be like <hi>Gideons</hi> proclamation in the eares of his faint hearted <hi>Souldiers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 7.3.</note> to make vs forsake our colours, and flie the field. If we begin to faint a little, let vs looke to our <hi>Leader. Consider him</hi> sayes the <hi>Apostle</hi> in the <hi>verse</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Text: <hi>Consider him</hi> both as our <hi>Leader,</hi> and as our <hi>Pay-master.</hi> As our <hi>Leader;</hi> for so we may bee bold to follow after him: Marching vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his conduct, it is not possible for
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177049:25"/>vs to misse-carry. <hi>Quales duces tales milites</hi> sayes one. Such as the <hi>Leaders</hi> are, such are commonly the <hi>Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chabrias. Plutarch. Apoph.</note> It hath beene a pretie question among curious wits, whether a <hi>Hart</hi> leading an armie of <hi>Lyons,</hi> or a <hi>Lyon</hi> leading an armie of <hi>Harts,</hi> whether of these would haue the victory if they should ioyne battell together. And the answere hath beene, that in all probabilitie of coniecture, the <hi>Harts</hi> would haue the victory, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause a <hi>Lyon</hi> is their <hi>Leader.</hi> For the courage of the <hi>Leader</hi> breaths resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into the <hi>Followers,</hi> and makes euen <hi>Cowards</hi> to be <hi>valiant.</hi> If thus, how happie are we then; sith though of our selues we are a sort of <hi>heartles Harts,</hi> amated with euery feare, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with euery danger, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we haue a <hi>Lyon</hi> to our <hi>Leader,</hi> the <hi>Lyon of the tribe of Iudah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 5 5.</note> that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer came from the field but hee brought home victorie with him. That which <hi>Dauid</hi> sung of <hi>Saul</hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177049:25"/>
               <hi>Ionathan,</hi> it may more truely be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to him.
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 1.22.</note>
               <hi>His bow neuer turned backe, his sword neuer came home emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> And therefore as <hi>Alexander</hi> said of <hi>Antipater,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tuto dormivi, vigilauit An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipater. Plut. Apoph.</note> when he betooke him one night to his Cabbin; <hi>That so long as Antipater watcht, he might be bold to sleepe;</hi> so may we say (Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) when we goe after <hi>Christ</hi> into the battell; That as long as he leads the way, we need not be fearefull to follow. He both <hi>leads</hi> vs and <hi>fights</hi> for vs. <hi>Certantem inspectat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Psal. 32.</note>
               <hi>Deficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem subleuat</hi> sayes Saint <hi>Austen:</hi> He beholds vs when we fight, relieues vs when we faint. Considering we haue such a <hi>Leader</hi> to goe before vs, we neede not be discouraged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Consider him</hi> not onely as our <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> but as our <hi>Pay-master;</hi> wee shall haue a <hi>Pay</hi> from him that will bee worth our <hi>fighting</hi> for: when wee haue done our <hi>resistance,</hi> he will giue vs our <hi>recompence;</hi> he will honour vs with a <hi>Crowne,</hi> when we haue ended
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177049:26"/>our <hi>Combate. Pugna breuis, Corona im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marcescibilis:</hi> A momentany com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, but an immarcessible Crowne. Ah but yet it troubles vs to thinke that we must loose our blood in the quarrell; ah but let it neuer trouble vs to loose <hi>Ours for him,</hi> seeing it neuer troubled him to loose <hi>His for vs.</hi> Do you not remember what the people said of <hi>Dauid;</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.3. They said, <hi>His life was worth more then ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of theirs.</hi> So may wee say of <hi>Christs bloud; One drop</hi> of his, it is more precious then <hi>ten thousand Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of ours.</hi> Ours for him is but <hi>Ad attestationem fidei,</hi> To witnesse the profession of our faith: His for vs, <hi>Ad ablutionem peccati,</hi> To wash a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the guiltinesse of our sinne. As euer wee desire therefore to haue <hi>Christs bloud</hi> a sacrifice for vs, wee must be willing to offer <hi>ours</hi> as a sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for him. <hi>Lord Iesus,</hi> if thou wilt haue it so, make vs willing that it should be so. Let vs willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177049:26"/>to shed ours for thee, and bee thou graciously pleased to poure out thine vpon vs. <hi>Thy bloud be vpon vs, O Lord, thy bloud be vpon vs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 27.25.</note> Wee wish it not as the trayterous and truculent <hi>Iewes</hi> wish it; not the <hi>guilt</hi> of it: Oh no, not the <hi>guilt</hi> of it <hi>Lord,</hi> but the <hi>merit</hi> of it. <hi>The merit of thy blood,</hi> let that be vpon the heads of vs all, and vpon the heads of our children for euer.</p>
            <p>So now I haue done with the <hi>Text</hi> in the sence that the <hi>Apostle</hi> meant it, showne you (as I can) what belongs to the <hi>spirituall resistance;</hi> to the <hi>fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the good fight of Faith.</hi> A <hi>fight</hi> that we are all called to, in being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to be <hi>Christians,</hi> and from the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of which, there is none of vs that must looke to be exempted: Not the <hi>youngest,</hi> not the <hi>oldest,</hi> not the <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest.</hi> Not the <hi>youngest,</hi> for euen chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as soone as they be borne, they haue presently their names put into the <hi>Check-rowle,</hi> and receiue from
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:177049:27"/>their <hi>Captaine</hi> their <hi>presse-money</hi> in their <hi>Baptisme.</hi> Not the <hi>oldest,</hi> for though the <hi>Romans</hi> had among them their <hi>Milites emeriti;</hi> Souldiers, who when they came to be of such an age they were discharged from the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the warres, and liued freely vpon their pensions; yet God <hi>(Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued)</hi> hath no such <hi>Souldiers</hi> in his warres; none that by reason of his age must looke to be discharged the field, or exempted from seruing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his banner: they must be his <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arij</hi> here, and till death giue them a discharge, they cannot be <hi>Emeriti.</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, not the <hi>weakest,</hi> whether made weake by <hi>sicknesse,</hi> or weake by <hi>sexe.</hi> The man that lies sicke vpon his bed, hee may fight and conquer in this battell, as well as he that can car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie armes into the field; yea, and they that are of the weaker <hi>sexe</hi> to, weake and tender <hi>women,</hi> though so tender that they dare not <hi>set the sole of their foote vpon the ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28.36</note> yet they haue
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177049:27"/>also their part to fight in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate. God calles them all to bee his <hi>Souldiers,</hi> and he hath his band of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazons</hi> among them. It is admirable to reade with what heroicall forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and valour a great many of them haue resisted. Their very <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers</hi> and <hi>Persecuters</hi> haue beene stricken with consternation and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement to behold it. This being the condition then that wee are all called to, it is this wee must all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for. Euery one get the <hi>Armour of God</hi> about him, that hee may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <hi>resist in the euill day.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephes. 6.13.</note> Thinke it not enough to loose your <hi>goods</hi> for <hi>Christs</hi> sake, but resolue to lose your <hi>blouds</hi> likewise, if he wil bring you to the altar. As <hi>Lorinus</hi> writes of <hi>Iohan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Eleemosynarius,</hi> that when the people wondered to see how benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and bountifull hee was, in the sustaining and succouring of poore <hi>Christians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lorin in</hi> 1. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist. Ioh. cap.</hi> 3.</note>
               <hi>Oh but brethren</hi> (saith hee) <hi>I haue not yet shed my blood for you as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:177049:28"/>my Master hath commanded me.</hi> Learn you all the like resolution: Learne to be <hi>strong in the Lord, and in the power of his might:</hi> Feare not <hi>Tortures,</hi> feare not <hi>Tyrants;</hi> say with Saint <hi>Paul; My life is not deare vnto me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 20.24.</note>
               <hi>so I may fulfill my course with ioy.</hi> And let it be with you as with Saint <hi>Chrysostome;</hi> when his enemies threatned him with tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and with death; what could one say that stood by? Neuer threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten these things to him; <hi>Nihil timet Chrysostomus nisi peccatum: Chrysostom</hi> is afraide of nothing but of sinne. So hauing <hi>quitted your selues like men,</hi> a <hi>Crowne of righteousnesse shall bee giuen you;</hi> and when you haue <hi>finished your course</hi> in the <hi>Church militant,</hi> you shal bee taken vp into the <hi>Church trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>And now I must humbly entreate of you, to lend me your patience yet one quarter of an houre more, that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177049:28"/>I may worke ouer my <hi>Text</hi> once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and apply it a little to our owne purpose, as at first I promised it. I haue giuen you the <hi>kernell</hi> of it alreadie, but now I must make meat of the <hi>shell.</hi> It is not like the <hi>huske of an Acorne,</hi> good for nothing but for the Hogges; but like the <hi>mace about the nutmeg,</hi> fragrant and sauoury. Briefly, it is of vse in the <hi>Letter,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Allegory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To speake according to the <hi>Letter</hi> therefore: Looke what the <hi>Apostle</hi> said to these <hi>Souldiers,</hi> the same I may say to you, as you are <hi>Souldiers</hi> in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother kinde, not <hi>Church-Souldiers,</hi> but <hi>Field-Souldiers;</hi> men of the <hi>mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary profession,</hi> as well as members of the <hi>militant Congregation.</hi> Your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession is Honourable, your designes generous, your preparations wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and noble; but <hi>you haue not resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted vnto bloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You haue not]</hi> Now blessed be God you haue not. I repeate it not by
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:177049:29"/>way of <hi>exprobration,</hi> but by way of <hi>congratulation.</hi> It is not any reproach to you at all, but it is the <hi>mercy</hi> of God to you; his <hi>mercy</hi> to vs as well as to you. Oh how much are wee bound vnto him! that wee haue so long sitten vnder our <hi>Vines and Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees</hi> in peace; that we haue heard of <hi>no violence</hi> all this while,
<note place="margin">Psal. 144.15.</note>
                  <hi>no leading in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to captiuity, no complaining nor crying in our streetes. Blessed are the people,</hi> saith the <hi>Prophet, that be in such a case.</hi> And <hi>blessed be the Lord our God</hi> (say I) that we are in this case. Happie, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie it is with vs, that wee know not what the miseries of warre meane.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>— <hi>En quo discordia ciues</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Virgil. Aeglog.</hi> 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Perduxit miseros.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>They bee sad and tragicall effects that warres doe bring forth. I neuer read them more wofully described, then by the Pen of the <hi>Prophet; La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> 5. It is a bleeding complaint that he makes there. He complaines how their <hi>Inheritances were all turned
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177049:29"/>to strangers, and their houses to Aliants. Children were left fatherlesse, Mothers were left widowes. The water that they drunke, they were faine to buy it with money, and the bread that they eate, to get it with the perill of their liues. Their neckes were held vnder persecution, and their skinnes were blacke like an Ouen. Seruants were set to rule ouer them, and there was none to deliuer them out of bondage There Virgines were rauished, and their Women defiled in the very streetes of their Cities. Their Princes were hanged vp by the hands, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their Elders were dishonoured: Their young men were put to grind, and their tender children broken vnder the burden that they carried. They had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iudgement in their gates, nor ioy at their feasts.</hi> Worse then all this, the house of God was laide wast, and the Congregations of the Saints were dispersed. <hi>The Mountaine of Syon was left desolate, and the Foxes ran vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</hi> Such be the miseries of <hi>warre:</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:177049:30"/>such the hauocke and spoile that the Sword brings.</p>
               <p>And yet <hi>dulce bellum inexpertis:</hi> Warre is sweete for all this, to them that know it not. To them that know it not indeede. But it is Gods sweete mercie to vs that we know it not. You <hi>play</hi> well as you <hi>play</hi> now. It was a <hi>bloudy play</hi> that we reade of, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. betweene the seruants of <hi>Ishbosheth</hi> and the seruants of <hi>Dauid. Let the young men rise and play before vs,</hi> saith <hi>Abner</hi> to <hi>Ioab:</hi> And what was the <hi>play</hi> they had? <hi>Euery one tooke another by the head, and thrust his sword through his side.</hi> Long may you all sit, before you be bidden rise to any such <hi>play.</hi> Let the glorie of it bee what it will. I confesse there is a great deale of glorie atchieued in the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary seruice of a iust warre. But what said <hi>Iehoash</hi> to <hi>Amasiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 14.10. <hi>Brag of glory and tarry at home.</hi> Beloued, I wish the same vnto you; That you may all tarry at home stil,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:177049:30"/>and bee content with the <hi>glorie</hi> that you haue. Neuer may you come to that honor (which yet many a braue Souldier hath counted his best ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) to shew what <hi>wounds</hi> and <hi>scars</hi> you haue brought from the field with you. But goe fairely on (as you doe) with these same <hi>Salmacida proe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> these same friendly frayes, and peacefull skirmishes that you are in, from whence at night you may come home againe <hi>Sine sanguine,</hi> though perhaps not <hi>Sine sudore;</hi> sweating perhaps, but yet not blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Neuer may it be saide of you, that <hi>you haue resisted vnto blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well, this is the <hi>mercy of God</hi> to you yet, that you haue <hi>not hitherto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted.</hi> But are we sure it will be thus alwaies? Shall <hi>Ianus Temple</hi> be still shut? or haue we any <hi>Pattent</hi> sealed vs of our peace? Is there now no feare of any danger? nor no neede of any preparation? Are we bidden, as it is <hi>Esay</hi> 2.4. <hi>to breake our speares into plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shares,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177049:31"/>or our swords into sithes?</hi> Or as it is <hi>Michah</hi> 4.3. Hath it beene said to vs that <hi>wee shall not learne to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more?</hi> Some may obiect thus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps; <hi>Non necessarij milites, quia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunt hostes:</hi> Wee neede no <hi>Souldiers,</hi> because we haue no <hi>enemies.</hi> I would we had not: but euery wise man that hath <hi>his eyes in his head,</hi> will easilie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that we haue both neede to feare, and cause to prepare. Wee know the <hi>Children of Edom</hi> well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,
<note place="margin">Psal. 137.7.</note> what they haue heretofore <hi>cried against Ierusalem.</hi> Wee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what <hi>Balak the King of Moah hath deuised,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mich. 6.5.</note>
                  <hi>and what Balaam the sonne of Beor hath counselled. Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> they haue heretofore confederated against <hi>England,</hi> like <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hadad,</hi> against <hi>Iudah.</hi> If we need feare no <hi>inuasions,</hi> whence come our <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons?</hi> Come they not both out of one <hi>forge?</hi> are they not both hammered vpon one <hi>Anuile?</hi> Sure they that <hi>shoote</hi> at vs in a <hi>vault,</hi> they would
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:177049:31"/>
                  <hi>shoote</hi> at vs in a <hi>field</hi> if they durst. They would ramme their <hi>powder</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>barrels of steele;</hi> as well as into <hi>bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels of wood.</hi> Wee neede not doubt therefore but we haue <hi>enemies.</hi> Wee may rather doubt what <hi>friends</hi> wee haue, then what <hi>enemies</hi> we haue.</p>
               <p>Besides this, what shall we thinke of the many <hi>prodigious and portentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous signes</hi> that wee haue latelie seene &amp; heard of;
<note place="margin">Vide Gallo-Belgici nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storicam pro anno praesen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti.</note> as if <hi>Nature</hi> were growne monstrous? Strange <hi>Comets</hi> in the aire, strange <hi>concussions</hi> of the Earth, strange <hi>diseases</hi> vpon the bodies of men: <hi>Waters</hi> strangely turned into <hi>blood.</hi> A whole <hi>Towne</hi> with all the Inhabitants of it, most strangelie swallowed vp into the ground; not one soule in it left aliue, nor so much as any Monument of it remaining to be seene? Shall we thinke these be all <hi>Mutes</hi> and <hi>Blancks?</hi> and that God speaks nothing to vs in them? Think it who will, I will not.</p>
               <p>It might bee obserued also, how
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:177049:32"/>the hand of God hath been lifted vp to strike many great <hi>Princes</hi> of late.
<note place="margin">Maximilianus Archidux Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>striae.</note> A great <hi>Duke of Austria,</hi> a great <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour</hi> and <hi>Empresse</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> a great <hi>Queene</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> and that which I cannot yet speake of, but with trembling and ioy: the verie <hi>Crowne of our head,</hi> it was falling, it was falling. He that is the <hi>light of our eyes,</hi> and the <hi>breath of our nostrils,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whose gracious shadow wee are all preserued; his <hi>light</hi> was almost quencht, his <hi>breath</hi> was almost taken from him. Oh what a gap had there then beene made for the <hi>Enemy</hi> to haue stept in? wee might then haue felt to our cost, what neede there would haue beene of <hi>preparation for resistance:</hi> But as <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Epaphrodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2.27.</note>
                  <hi>The Lord hath showen mercy vnto him; and not to him, but to vs also</hi> (mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified and blessed be his name for it) in vouchsafing him recouerie. Our <hi>vnthankfulnesse</hi> for him, had almost lost him. Let me speake freelie. There
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:177049:32"/>are a sort of <hi>winter grashoppers</hi> among vs; a generation that is euer murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and repining: They consider not what store of <hi>blessings</hi> they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, but still they are complaining of <hi>burdens</hi> and <hi>grieuances;</hi> still obiecting that the former times were better then these. There may a day come, when they shal wish to see the things they see now, and they shall not see them. In the meane time, little doe they know what an inualuable losse it would haue beene, if this <hi>Diamond</hi> had fallen out of our <hi>Ring. Oh thou preseruer of men, hide him still as a cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen shaft in thy quiuer, and binde his soule vp in the bundle of life. As for the soules of his enemies, let them be cast like a stone out of the middle of a sling.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.29.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I haue one thing more to name yet, that tels vs what great cause we haue to feare; greater this then any of the other. Will you aske what it is? It is the <hi>invndation of Sinne,</hi> that so immeasurably ouerflowes in all
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:177049:33"/>places of this land. Oh the crying sinnes, the crying sinnes of this land; they will neuer let heauen be at rest, till it haue sent them a scourge. It is an admirable peice of newes that our late <hi>Gallo-Belgicus</hi> reports about the towne of <hi>Pleurs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 4.</note> I told you of euen now; that was so strangely subuerted vpon the sudden, and lies buried to this day vnder it's owne ashes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope of any possible restaurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. A while after the subuersion of it, diuers neighbourers that repaired thither would needes attempt to dig into the ground that they might see what they could finde. Among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things that they found, God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected them to a <hi>Stone,</hi> which when they had taken vp, they saw some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing written vpon it in <hi>Hebrew let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> as if (like the <hi>Tables of Stone,</hi> that were giuen to <hi>Moses</hi> in mount <hi>Sinai</hi>) it had beene grauen with Gods own finger. The writing was this;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus sayth the Lord; My word is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:177049:33"/>like fire, and like a hammer breaking the Rockes. Goe out of Babylon, and euery one looke to the sauing of his owne soule. Let none winke at his sinnes, for the vengeance will come, and all shall be rewarded according to their wickednesse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beloued, I desire not to sit like an omnious <hi>Rauen</hi> vpon the house-top, croaking out any fatall presages of one or other euill that may come vpon the <hi>Land</hi> that we liue in: The Lord turne it from vs in mercie, and rather send it to fall vpon the heads of our enemies. But when vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery <hi>Stone</hi> in the street, we may see the <hi>sinnes of the Land</hi> to be written,
<note place="margin">Ier. 17.1.</note> written as with <hi>a pen of Iron, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as with the poynt of a Diamond;</hi> how can we but feare, least there be a <hi>stone</hi> falling from heauen, vpon which our <hi>Iudgement</hi> is also written, the destruction &amp; ruine of our <hi>Land</hi> engrauen with Gods owne finger shortly to be accomplisht.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:177049:34"/>
               <p>Well then beloued: Seeing there be so many things that make vs to feare danger, how can any <hi>preparate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> be vnnecessary to preuent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? To God ward our onely <hi>prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> must be by <hi>repentance.</hi> But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst other enemies; such as you are now prouiding, that you may be readie for <hi>resistance.</hi> Looke what the <hi>Apostle</hi> here requires of his <hi>Souldiers,</hi> the very like vnto it is expected from you. A <hi>resisting,</hi> and a <hi>persisting. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi> for the one: <hi>Resolution</hi> in the other.</p>
               <p>Remember first; It is but a place of <hi>resistance</hi> that you stand in. You must onely prepare to <hi>resist,</hi> not to <hi>assault.</hi> As it is in the other combate, so in this. We are not <hi>Assaulters</hi> in the other but onely <hi>Resisters.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther must we be here. <hi>Resist</hi> we may, if another offer vs any violence: But vnlesse violence be offered vs, we haue no warrant to <hi>assault.</hi> Now <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance</hi> first of all, it must be made
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:177049:34"/>you know against them that be <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> You must therefore take heed of it among <hi>your selues.</hi> Among your selues, let all vnitie and concord bee preserued. Let not the least murmure of any <hi>resistance</hi> be heard of. <hi>Agesilaus</hi> was asked the question, why the cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Sparta</hi> was built without wals. Poynting to the <hi>Cittizens</hi> he answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; <hi>En muros Spartae,</hi> Behold the wals of <hi>Sparta. Spartaes Cittizens are Spartaes wals.</hi> As long as the <hi>Citti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> be vnanimous among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, they feare not the inuasion of any <hi>Enemy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Marry; <hi>resistance</hi> against an <hi>Enemy</hi> and so <hi>Preparation for resistance;</hi> that is both <hi>necessary</hi> and <hi>honourable:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. It is <hi>necessary;</hi> because there can be no safetie without it. In what a case was the land of <hi>Israell,</hi> when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <hi>fortie thousand of the people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg. 5.8.</note>
                  <hi>there was not a speare, nor a shield to be seene?</hi> The sight of a weapon (we say) scars a Theife. What theiuerie
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:177049:35"/>there is in hand we know not: But we heare of great <hi>preparations</hi> that others make abroad. Beloued, It cannot be amisse for vs to haue an eye to our owne safetie, though we suspect not their fidelitie: Though we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare not <hi>for them,</hi> we may prepare <hi>with them.</hi> We may be in readinesse to <hi>resist,</hi> if they offer any <hi>assault</hi> vnto <hi>vs,</hi> though for our owne parts we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to offer any <hi>assault</hi> vnto <hi>them.</hi> Be none so absurd as to obiect, <hi>We put our confidence in God, and we trust he will defend vs.</hi> Grant we doe so,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Dei. lib.</hi> 16. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note> yet for all that; <hi>Si periculum quod cauere possumus, non cavemus;</hi> If wee preuent not those dangers our selues which wee haue meanes to preuent, we doe rather <hi>Deum tentare,</hi> then in <hi>Deo sperare;</hi> we do rather tempt God then trust God. But what is <hi>Muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> without <hi>Men?</hi> Or what are <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons</hi> without <hi>Warriours?</hi> As good no weopons at all, as no dexteritie to vse them. It is reported of <hi>Lycurgus,</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:177049:35"/>that he trained vp the children of the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plut. in vita Lycur.</note> when they once came to be seauen yeers of age, in all kinds of martiall and warlike exercises; So that it was a wonder to behold their actiuitie and valour. And very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blable it is, that the like discipline was vsed among the <hi>Iewes</hi> themselues. For 1. <hi>Chro</hi> 12.38. it is wonderfull to obserue, what a multitude of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Warriours they had among them: <hi>Three hundred and two and twentie thousand, euery one able to lead an Armte.</hi> Where there is this abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to performe, there will bee the more boldnesse to attempt. <hi>Nemo facere metuit, qui se bene didicisse confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit,</hi> none will be afraid to fight, that knowes he hath skill to fight. Mary, if one haue a weapon, and no skill to vse it; alas, what shall we say to him? We may say, as it was said to one that had gotten him a faire <hi>Buckler,</hi> gaily guilded and trimmed: one told him, he did well to bestow such cost
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:177049:36"/>vpon his <hi>Buckler.</hi> It was a signe <hi>that he trusted more to his Buckler then to his sword.</hi> So then; it is <hi>necessary</hi> you see, that there should be <hi>preparation for resistance;</hi> that there should be both <hi>armes</hi> in readinesse, and <hi>men</hi> in readinesse. For there can be no safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie without it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As it is <hi>necessary,</hi> so it is <hi>honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</hi> What nobler or more honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable exercises then such as these, to him that hath any masculine spirit in him, him that carries the mind of a man? Shall he liue like a luskish <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donian,</hi> or like an effeminated <hi>Syba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite,</hi> languishing in ease, and <hi>rauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> out his time in courtship and dalliance? Shall he doe nothing but sit singing and sonnetting among <hi>Ladies</hi> and <hi>Gentlewomen,</hi> or perhaps stretch his armes now and then at <hi>Shittlecock</hi> or <hi>Biliards?</hi> Shall he bee like that <hi>Mindyrides</hi> that <hi>Seneca</hi> writes of,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de ira. cap.</hi> 25.</note> that could not endure to see a man digge: <hi>Latus condoluit,</hi> it
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:177049:36"/>made his sides ake to see him: And when he lay streaking himselfe vpon a bed of Roses, he complained he lay vneasily,
<note place="margin">Vetuit illum, opus in conspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu suo facere.</note>
                  <hi>quod folijs rosae duplicatis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubuisset;</hi> because he felt a leafe dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnder him? Such be a sort of the feather-headded Gallants that walke the streetes of our Cittie: <hi>Women like men,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Nahum</hi> cals them; <hi>Thy men within thee are like women.</hi> Nah. 3.13. <hi>Virorum faemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, faeminarum viri,</hi> as one sayes: women among men, and onely men among women. Make <hi>Captaines</hi> and <hi>Colonels</hi> of these: They will be euen such as the Prophet speakes of there: <hi>Captaine Grashopper,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vers. 17.</note> and <hi>Colonell-Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cust.</hi> They will not dare to trie a battell with <hi>Aesops</hi> frogges, if they come against them with Bul-rushes. As much in effect is sayd of them, by <hi>Nahum</hi> himselfe. He likens them to <hi>Fig-trees</hi> when the <hi>first ripe Figges</hi> are vpon them, <hi>Shake them, and they drop into the mouth of the Eater.</hi> So
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:177049:37"/>these: draw but a sword at them, they fall downe at the foote of the <hi>Assaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What an honour is it therefore to you of this Societie, that you haue so nobly engaged your selues in an exercise of this nature, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed both for the <hi>safetie</hi> and for the <hi>glory</hi> of the Kingdome. Me thinkes I cannot say whether you make a better shew, when you are <hi>togati,</hi> or <hi>armati,</hi> in your gownes, or in your armes; whether when you are habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as <hi>Senators,</hi> or accoutred as <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers;</hi> whether in your <hi>Citie-liueries,</hi> or in your <hi>Captaines colours.</hi> In the one, we see the happie fruites of a well ordered peace: In this other, generous preparations for a lawfull warre. In the one, you maintaine the honorable seates of <hi>Iustice.</hi> In this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you aduance glorious <hi>Tropheys</hi> vnto <hi>Fortitude.</hi> And doubtlesse hee is the onely absolute and compleate man, in whom is the concurrence
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:177049:37"/>of those two vertues, <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Valour,</hi> he that is both an <hi>Vlysses</hi> at home, and an <hi>Achilles</hi> abroad; he that hath both a <hi>head</hi> for Counsell, and a <hi>hand</hi> for action. For <hi>Gentlemen in the Country,</hi> to haue raised such a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, and erected such an exercise, though it had beene worthily done of them, yet lesse commendable in them, then in you. In regard of their habitation, education, condition, probabilitie of reason sayes, they bee better accommodated. You haue the greater honour therfore that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the qualitie you are, rather <hi>Marchant-like,</hi> then <hi>Martiall-like men,</hi> fitter for an <hi>Appij forum,</hi> then for a <hi>Campus Martius;</hi> that yet you do so willinglie offer your selues in so he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall a seruice, follow it with such industrie, maintaine it with such charge, that the world may see your hearts are not altogether set vpon your ease, and vpon your profit. There rises a better report by this
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:177049:38"/>meanes to you of <hi>London,</hi> then to them of <hi>Laish.</hi> You know how the <hi>spies of Israell</hi> found and reported them, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 18.10. <hi>Terrafructuosa, gens otiosa:</hi> A fruitfull Land, but a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie people; and that made them a prey to their enemie.</p>
               <p>What now remaines, but that you be animated with all possible excita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and encouragements, to goe on in your strength, and to maintain what you haue begun? as you haue prepared for <hi>resisting,</hi> so to be reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute in <hi>persisting?</hi> I wish nothing may be wanting vnto you, that may any way encourage you. To say truth, wee should all ioine together, to set forward so noble a designe, some in one kind, some in another. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what a reuerend <hi>Diuine</hi> said; one, who while he liued, he was the <hi>Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Oracle</hi> of our <hi>Cambridge V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersity.</hi> At a certaine <hi>Commencement time,</hi> when there was a <hi>Musicke act</hi> to bee kept, they of the <hi>Act</hi> made re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:177049:38"/>that they might beginne with their <hi>Musicke.</hi> Hee would not suffer it, but according to the wonted lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable custome, hee would haue the <hi>Diuinity</hi> to beginne. Nay, saith he;
<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers. Illinos audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant dicentes quia canere nō possumus; Nos illos au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diemus ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentes quia dicere non possunt.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>They shall first heare vs dispute, because we cannot sing; afterward we will heare them sing, because they cannot dispute.</hi> I apply it to my purpose thus. That which one is not able to doe, let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother helpe to doe. There are a sort of wealthy Citizens, that are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or not fit perhaps, to doe <hi>perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> seruice in this action. What they cannot doe by <hi>person,</hi> let them doe by <hi>purse.</hi> Some that haue not gold to offer, are willing to offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. Others that are willing to spare themselues, let them offer their gold. Spare from your vanities and superfluities, from the pride of your apparell, the pompe of your shewes, the luxurie of your feasts; spare, and cast into this treasurie, where you shall but lay vp a <hi>stocke for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:177049:39"/>safety.</hi> Remember, it is not your wealth that will deliuer you in the day of battle: deliuer you? Nay, it will rather betray you, rather bee a baite for your enemie, then a bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke to your selues. Thus it was with <hi>Hezekiah.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. King. 20.13</note> The sight of his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, had almost lost him his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.
<note place="margin">Plut in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par. Hannib. &amp; Scip.</note> And so <hi>Hannibal</hi> told <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> when <hi>Antiochus</hi> shewed him what an army he had prouided, rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie stored with gold and siluer; but otherwise men of no extraordinarie either courage or strength. He asked him, if he thought that armie would not be sufficient for the <hi>Romans? Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal</hi> answered him; <hi>Yes, that it would, though the Romans were neuer so couet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:</hi> Intimating, there was spoile e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to enrich them, though not force enough to withstand them. You therefore that cannot be Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, make Souldiers: be helpefull with your <hi>purses,</hi> seeing you cannot be seruiceable in your <hi>persons.</hi> Let
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:177049:39"/>your <hi>Mammon</hi> helpe to fight for you, and <hi>make you friends</hi> of it that way.</p>
               <p>We for our parts, we that are of poore <hi>Leuies</hi> Tribe, we will helpe you what we can too. Though wee cannot by our <hi>purses,</hi> nor though we cannot by our <hi>persons,</hi> yet we will helpe you by our <hi>prayers.</hi> We will carry the <hi>Arke of God</hi> for you when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer you goe into the battell. If you doe <hi>nostram causam agere gladijs,</hi> we will <hi>vestram agere precibus.</hi> If you fight for vs, we will pray for you: We will <hi>hold vp our hands</hi> to God for you, as <hi>Moses</hi> did for <hi>Ioshua,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 17.11.</note> when he fought against <hi>Amalek.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For your selues last of all; Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to be your selues still;
<note place="margin">Iudg. 6.12.</note> and (as the <hi>Angell</hi> to <hi>Gideon</hi>) <hi>the Lord be with you, you valiant men.</hi> It is true, there hath beene yet but little proofe of your valour. I wish as I wisht be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; that there neuer may be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. If greater must be, the God that
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:177049:40"/>sittes aboue, strengthen you with courage, &amp; crown you with victory. You must looke to find a difference then, betweene those skirmishes and these velitations. But that which was <hi>Senecaes</hi> resolution, let that bee yours. I affect not (sayes he) the contentions of warre, yet if I cannot auoyd it,
<note place="margin">Seneca in Epist.</note> but that I must be engaged in them, <hi>&amp; famem &amp; frigus, &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia quae belli necessitas adfert, genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se feram;</hi> be it hunger or colde, or whatsoeuer the necessitie of the war shall cast vpon me, I will freely and generously beare it. Carry in one word, this comfort away with you: He that dies a good <hi>Souldier,</hi> dies a good <hi>Martyr.</hi> It need not trouble you though you die not in your beds, if you be sure you die not in your sinnes.</p>
               <p>The Lord strengthen vs all, to be good <hi>Soldiers</hi> in the battels to which he shall call vs, and so to <hi>fight the good fight of faith,</hi> that hauing couragious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:177049:40"/>
                  <hi>resisted,</hi> constantly <hi>persisted,</hi> euen to the effusion of our bloud, we may in the end receiue a Crowne of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse from him, who <hi>by his own bloud hath redeemed vs vnto God.</hi> So shall we sing songs of victorie to him that hath got the victorie for vs, <hi>bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, and glory, and wisedome, and thankes, and honour, and power, and might, to our Lord Iesus Christ, for euer and euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2. SAM. 10.12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Be strong and valiant for our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and for the Citties of our God and let the Lord doe that which is good in his eyes.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:177049:41"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177049:42"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>